<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nathan&#39;s House of Code</title>
    <link>https://ndonolli.github.io/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Nathan&#39;s House of Code</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tanksuzuki&#34;&gt;Asuka Suzuki&lt;/a&gt; 2016</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 15:04:06 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ndonolli.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Minesweeper Interview Problem</title>
      <link>https://ndonolli.github.io/post/minesweeper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 15:04:06 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ndonolli.github.io/post/minesweeper/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I have a friend who was asked, during a coding interview, to write their own version of minesweeper from scratch.  I found this anecdote amusing, as I have never encountered this problem during any interview I&amp;rsquo;ve ever taken.  Sure, I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten take home assignments that generally require real-world tasks, but never making a game from scratch.  And according to this friend, this was a &lt;em&gt;whiteboard&lt;/em&gt; interview.  Tall tale or not, it&amp;rsquo;s still a pretty neat story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You tell me to recreate minesweeper on a whiteboard, and my first thought is &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;well, at least the fall from this floor will definitely kill me&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.  But hey - I thought about what it would entail and figured I&amp;rsquo;d give myself my own coding interview, using basic javascript to create a basic minesweeper implementation in, oh say, an hour.  This post describes how I did it - the good, the bad, and the ugly - and how you can do it too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to follow along, check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ndonolli/minesweeper-example&#34;&gt;github repository&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;../../projects/minesweeper/&#34;&gt;live example&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-whiteboard&#34;&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Whiteboard&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, right.  I did this problem on a &lt;em&gt;computer&lt;/em&gt;, touching two files: &lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;index.js&lt;/code&gt;.  I gave myself a few restrictions to make it feel more like an interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic javascript only - no frameworks, no libraries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do it within a time limit (60 minutes give or take)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plan of action was to include all logic, from the board data to the creation of HTML elements, inside the &lt;code&gt;index.js&lt;/code&gt; file, and give my &lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt; file simple container elements to which I could append my rendered minesweeper board.  I planned to organize the board as a &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;table&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; of &amp;ldquo;tiles&amp;rdquo;, all of which would hold game data and be subscribed to event listeners to handle clicks.  This is but one of many ways to structure the game. I encourage you, dear reader, to determine a better way to do it than this idiot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For reference, here is what my &lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt; looked like at this point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;index-html&#34;&gt;index.html&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-html&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;meta charset=&amp;quot;utf-8&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;meta name=&amp;quot;viewport&amp;quot; content=&amp;quot;width=device-width&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;script src=&amp;quot;https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/jquery/3.2.1/jquery.js&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;script src=&amp;quot;index.js&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;title&amp;gt;Minesweeper&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;MINESWEEPER!!&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;div id=&amp;quot;table-container&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;!--minesweeper goes here--&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;You&amp;rsquo;re using jQuery?? That&amp;rsquo;s cheating!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know, I know.  My reasoning here is that I&amp;rsquo;m using jQuery as a familiar way to query and create simple DOM elements, and not utilizing the full capabilities of the library.  An interviewer would be more concerned with application design and logic anyway.  Which brings us to -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-javascript&#34;&gt;The Javascript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When writing a game, a common design pattern is to organize game objects as classes, in an OOP (Object-Oriented Programming) paradigm.  Given the time limit, and simplicity of the game, I deemed this method overkill for this specific case.  Instead, I took a more procedural approach, with a main function running sequential functions to initialize the game.  The structure of &lt;code&gt;index.js&lt;/code&gt; would look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;function makeBoard() {
  // generate data for minesweeper board
}

function renderBoard() {
  // create HTML elements and append to #table-container element
}

function initGameRules() {
  // initialize game rules
}

function initGame() {
  // &amp;quot;main&amp;quot; function
  makeBoard();
  renderBoard();
  initGameRules();
}

$(document).ready(() =&amp;gt; {
  initGame();
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be some differences, but ultimately this is how I decided to organize the code.  In a sense, it still bears some resemblance to OOP style code in a language like Java, with everything falling under an abstract &amp;ldquo;&lt;code&gt;Board&lt;/code&gt;&amp;rdquo; class and having a &lt;code&gt;main&lt;/code&gt; method (in this case, &lt;code&gt;initGame&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;making-the-board&#34;&gt;Making the Board&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing I began working on was the &lt;code&gt;makeBoard&lt;/code&gt; function, since I already had an idea of how I wanted the data structure of the minesweeper board to be organized.  I wanted to create a two-dimentional vector system using nested arrays, where accessing a tile piece at &lt;code&gt;(x, y)&lt;/code&gt; could be done using the bracket notation - ex. &lt;code&gt;board[x][y]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;function makeBoard(n, bombRate) {
  // creates n * n board of array vectors
  // @param {n} &amp;lt;int&amp;gt; Specify dimension
  // @param {bombRate} &amp;lt;float&amp;gt; Probability of bombs
  // @return &amp;lt;Array&amp;gt; &amp;quot;board&amp;quot; of &amp;lt;td&amp;gt; elements indexed at board[i][j]

  let board = [];

  return board;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the atomic level, each element would be an object containing information about the the tile piece, such as whether the tile holds a bomb, how many bombs are in adjacent, etc.  This object I would eventually store in a &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;td&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; element&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;data&lt;/code&gt; attribute, which would later be mapped to a &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;table&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; element in &lt;code&gt;renderBoard&lt;/code&gt;.  Initially I didn&amp;rsquo;t think so far ahead, though.  The first step was to create the board data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put the initialization logic within an &lt;code&gt;init&lt;/code&gt; function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;function init() {
  // initializes board and randomizes bombs
  // @param none
  // @return void
  for (let i = 0; i &amp;lt; n; i++) {
    board.push([]);
    for (let j = 0; j &amp;lt; n; j++) {
      let isBomb = Math.random() &amp;gt; bombRate ? false : true;
      let $space = $(&#39;&amp;lt;td&amp;gt;&#39;).data({
        bomb: isBomb,
        clicked: false,
      });
      board[i].push($space);
    }
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;code&gt;init&lt;/code&gt; function populates our array &lt;code&gt;board&lt;/code&gt; with &amp;ldquo;bomb&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;no bomb&amp;rdquo; &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;td&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; elements randomized by the &lt;code&gt;bombRate&lt;/code&gt; argument passed into our parent function.  Taking cues from the existing procedural design pattern, I decided to move the logic required to calculate the adjacent bombs to another function - named &lt;code&gt;calculateAdjacent&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get ready, this one is a bit of a doosey:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;function calculateAdjacent(i, j) {
  // called with coords of one piece and calculates adjacent bombs
  // used within initAdjacent
  // @param {i} &amp;lt;int&amp;gt; vertical coordinate
  // @param {j} &amp;lt;int&amp;gt; horizontal coordinate
  // @return void
  let adjacent = 0;

  // get the top and bottom rows first
  for (let x = j - 1; x &amp;lt; j + 2; x++) {
    // try blocks to bypass errors when board[i][j] is undefined.
    try {
      if (board[i-1][x].data().bomb) adjacent++; // top
    } catch(e) {} // no handler needed, using catch like a &#39;continue&#39;
    try {
      if (board[i+1][x].data().bomb) adjacent++; // bottom
    } catch(e) {}
  }
    // left and right adjacent
  try {
    if (board[i][j-1].data().bomb) adjacent++;
  } catch(e) {} // again, no handler is needed

  try {
    if (board[i][j+1].data().bomb) adjacent++;
  } catch(e) {} // but a catch block is necessary
  
  return adjacent;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not too proud of this code, primarily due to the abuse of the &lt;code&gt;try...catch&lt;/code&gt; blocks.  The reason for them is this: if I&amp;rsquo;m checking for adjacent bombs for tile &lt;code&gt;(i, j)&lt;/code&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;d need to check the perimeter of &lt;code&gt;i - 1&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;i + 1&lt;/code&gt; as well as &lt;code&gt;j - 1&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;j + 1&lt;/code&gt; for bombs.  If I&amp;rsquo;m checking a tile on, say, the top edge of the board, then &lt;code&gt;i - 1&lt;/code&gt; is undefined, which throws a error that short-circuits the for loop.  By encapsulating the check within a &lt;code&gt;try...catch&lt;/code&gt; block, we can disregard the errors and utilize the catch block as a &amp;ldquo;continue&amp;rdquo; for non-existing spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this an elegant solution?  Far from it.  However, it solved this isolated problem and allowed me to continue on without much delay.  If you&amp;rsquo;re following along, I challenge you to devise a better solution to this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, now that this &lt;code&gt;calculateAdjacent&lt;/code&gt; function works, I can use it in a &lt;code&gt;setAdjacent&lt;/code&gt; function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;function setAdjacent() {
  // traverses and calls calculateAdjacent() for each piece,
  // storing adjacent in piece object
  // @param none
  // @return void
  for (let i = 0; i &amp;lt; n; i++) {
    for (let j = 0; j &amp;lt; n; j++) {
      board[i][j].data().adjacent = calculateAdjacent(i, j);
    }
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that, we can call &lt;code&gt;init&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;setAdjacent&lt;/code&gt; before returning our &lt;code&gt;board&lt;/code&gt; of tile objects at the end of our &lt;code&gt;makeBoard&lt;/code&gt; function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;  // start the initialization captain!
  init();
  setAdjacent();
  return board;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;rendering-the-board&#34;&gt;Rendering the Board&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step is to render our &lt;code&gt;board&lt;/code&gt; of &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;td&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; elements to our HTML.  jQuery allows us to accomplish this with relatively little code.  Look:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;function renderBoard(board) {
  // renders board onto #tableContainer element
  // @param {board} &amp;lt;Array&amp;gt; board generated from makeBoard
  // @return void

  function generateGrid(board) {
    // appends board array (holding &amp;lt;td&amp;gt;) onto an html table element
    // @param {board} &amp;lt;Array&amp;gt; board generated from makeBoard
    // @return {$grid} &amp;lt;HTML Element&amp;gt; &amp;lt;table&amp;gt; elem with board &amp;lt;td&amp;gt; elems appended
    let $grid = $(&#39;&amp;lt;table&amp;gt;&#39;);

    board.forEach(elems =&amp;gt; {
      let $row = $(&#39;&amp;lt;tr&amp;gt;&#39;);
      $row.append(elems);
      $grid.append($row);
    })

    return $grid;
  }

  const $grid = generateGrid(board);
  $(&amp;quot;#table-container&amp;quot;).empty().append($grid);
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within &lt;code&gt;renderBoard&lt;/code&gt;, I declared a &lt;code&gt;generateGrid&lt;/code&gt; function, which appends each element of &lt;code&gt;board&lt;/code&gt; as a row in our minesweeper table.  The main process of &lt;code&gt;renderBoard&lt;/code&gt; declares the table using &lt;code&gt;generateGrid&lt;/code&gt; and appends it to the existing &lt;code&gt;#table-container&lt;/code&gt; element within &lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s almost time to take a deep breath and see where we stand.  Let&amp;rsquo;s put in some styling in our HTML so that our new rendered table will look nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;index-html-1&#34;&gt;index.html&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-html&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;meta charset=&amp;quot;utf-8&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;meta name=&amp;quot;viewport&amp;quot; content=&amp;quot;width=device-width&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;script src=&amp;quot;https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/jquery/3.2.1/jquery.js&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;script src=&amp;quot;index.js&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;style&amp;gt;
  h1 {
    text-align: center;
  }
  table {
    margin: 10px auto;
  }
  td {
    border: 1px solid;
    width: 50px;
    height: 50px;
    text-align: center;
  }
  #table-container {
    align-content: center;
  }
  &amp;lt;/style&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;title&amp;gt;Minesweeper&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;setting-the-game-rules&#34;&gt;Setting the Game Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re following along, then running your &lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt; at this point will give you an empty table.  However, clicking on the tiles does nothing.  If you recall, we stored the tile information within the HTML &amp;ldquo;data&amp;rdquo; attribute, which is nice because it allows our tiles to be empty HTML elements on the surface.  What I need now is to devise the logic whenever a tile is clicked - either to show the adjacent bombs, or to display the bomb if a bomb gets clicked.  Let&amp;rsquo;s do this withn the &lt;code&gt;initGameRules&lt;/code&gt; function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;index-js&#34;&gt;index.js&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;function initGameRules() {
  // sets click handlers for game logic
  // @param none
  // @return none
  function togglePiece(self) {
    // ...
  }

  function bombGoBoom() {
    // ...
  }

  $( &amp;quot;td&amp;quot; ).click(function() {
    togglePiece(this);
    if ($(this).data().bomb) bombGoBoom();
  });

}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what&amp;rsquo;s going on here - the main function of &lt;code&gt;initGameRules&lt;/code&gt; is the click handler defined at the end.  This handler is assigned to all our &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;td&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; elements (tiles) and does two things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Toggles the piece and displays whatever information is in its &lt;code&gt;data&lt;/code&gt; attribute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the tile is a bomb, then end the game with &lt;code&gt;bombGoBoom&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s build out these two functions then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;function togglePiece(self) {
  let space = $(self).data(), txt;
  space.clicked = true;

  if (space.bomb) {
    $(self).addClass(&#39;bomb&#39;);
    txt = &#39;bomb&#39;;
  } else {
    txt = space.adjacent;
  }
  $(self).text(txt);
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the record, the &lt;code&gt;self&lt;/code&gt; parameter refers to the clicked tile element, which is the &lt;code&gt;this&lt;/code&gt; context within the click handler we defined.  &lt;code&gt;togglePiece&lt;/code&gt; is not a method of the tile elements, so we can&amp;rsquo;t use &lt;code&gt;this&lt;/code&gt; within the function to refer to itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than that, all this function does is access the data attribute of the clicked tile, and renders the appropriate text - the number of adjacent bombs if the tile is clean, or the text &amp;ldquo;bomb&amp;rdquo; if the tile holds a bomb.  In the latter case, I also added a &amp;ldquo;bomb&amp;rdquo; class to that element, which can also help with some styling:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;index-html-2&#34;&gt;index.html&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-html&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;style&amp;gt;
  h1 {
    text-align: center;
  }
  table {
    margin: 10px auto;
  }
  td {
    border: 1px solid;
    width: 50px;
    height: 50px;
    text-align: center;
  }
  &amp;lt;!--add a bomb class--&amp;gt;
  .bomb {
      background-color: indianred;
  }
  #table-container {
    align-content: center;
  }
&amp;lt;/style&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now all bomb tiles will have a red background to differenciate them from other tiles.  And what better color for bombs than an offensive name like &lt;code&gt;indianred&lt;/code&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have one more piece of logic for our game rules - what happens when a bomb is clicked?  Well, the game should end. And at this point I was really running out of time.  What resulted was a hack:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;function bombGoBoom() {
  // bomb go boom 
  $(&#39;td&#39;).each((i, space) =&amp;gt; togglePiece(space));
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, not too proud of this one.  My &amp;ldquo;game over&amp;rdquo; logic was to just toggle all the tiles so you can see where the rest of the bombs were.  On one hand this works, on the other hand, we can no longer set appropriate conditions for winning or losing the game, as well as extending the game with different rules, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left this dirty code in here because, as developers, we need to embrace our shame and mistakes.  The world is not perfect, and sometimes code has got to ship.  As I showered myself clean of my disgrace (literally), I thought of several other ways I could have done this, but my time was up.  &lt;em&gt;Now it is your time.&lt;/em&gt;  If you are still following along with your own minesweeper project - please, please utilize a better solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;putting-it-all-together&#34;&gt;Putting it All Together&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrapping it up from here is trivial:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;function initGame(n, bombRate) {
  // call makeBoard
  const board = makeBoard(n, bombRate);
  // call the function that appends board to #table-container
  renderBoard(board);
  // initialize gameRules
  initGameRules();
}

$(document).ready(() =&amp;gt; {
  initGame(5, .25)
})
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;initGame&lt;/code&gt; will be called after the document loads with the hardcoded parameters &lt;code&gt;(5, .25)&lt;/code&gt;, which is &lt;code&gt;5&lt;/code&gt; for the board dimension and &lt;code&gt;.25&lt;/code&gt; for the probability of bombs.  Since I ran out of time, I did not implement a way for the end user to customize their minesweeper game.  I leave this to you, along with the rest of the features of this incomplete project.  Here are some challenges you can take on yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement a way for the player to set the board size and bomb probability themselves, and render a new game based on their input.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change the game win/lose logic, where the game is lost when a bomb is clicked, and the game is won when all non-bomb tiles have been clicked.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In real minesweeper, players can &amp;ldquo;flag&amp;rdquo; a tile they believe holds a bomb. Add this feature in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Last but not least, a time limit!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-thoughts&#34;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I learned from this little self-test was that a seemingly big problem can be approached easily with a solid design.  Even if the design has some pitfalls and code smells, it can allow you to follow through and finish a task in a timely manner.  That is an important skill for any software developer or engineer.  I hope you&amp;rsquo;ve learned something as well, if not at the very least how to make a simple game like minesweeper with vanilla javascript.  And who knows, maybe some day an interviewer will ask you to create minesweeper on a whiteboard.  My hope is that you will panic a little less.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let the fors flow through you</title>
      <link>https://ndonolli.github.io/post/let-the-fors/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2017 10:38:10 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ndonolli.github.io/post/let-the-fors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s wrong with &lt;code&gt;var&lt;/code&gt;?  Well, a great many things, but is it really that bad?  Kind of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;rsquo;t find any good reasons where &lt;code&gt;var&lt;/code&gt; gives you a legitimate advantage over &lt;code&gt;let&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt;.  All other major languages use block scoping, and with the ES6 initiative to welcome a new &lt;code&gt;class&lt;/code&gt; of developers who come from stricter, safer languages, the &lt;code&gt;var&lt;/code&gt; keyword will only cause confusion.  On top of that, the light restrictions of &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt; will enforce better paradigms like functional, data-driven programming and immutable data structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should absolutely use &lt;code&gt;let&lt;/code&gt; on for loops to block scope your iterator.  Here&amp;rsquo;s a case where using &lt;code&gt;var&lt;/code&gt; goes too far:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;var funcs = [];

for (var i = 0; i &amp;lt; 3; i++) {
  funcs[i] = function() {
    console.log(&amp;quot;value of i: &amp;quot; + i);
  }
}

funcs.forEach(func =&amp;gt; func.call());

// &amp;quot;value of i: 3&amp;quot;
// &amp;quot;value of i: 3&amp;quot;
// &amp;quot;value of i: 3&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh snap! Do you see it? That pesky &lt;code&gt;var&lt;/code&gt; declares &lt;code&gt;i&lt;/code&gt; as a global variable, so all functions in &lt;code&gt;func&lt;/code&gt; access it while it is equal to 3.  Wrap it in a function, it still doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter.  &amp;ldquo;But what about closure?&amp;rdquo; you ask, believing that each function in &lt;code&gt;func&lt;/code&gt; should hold its own &lt;code&gt;i&lt;/code&gt; in context.  This should be true, and expected since closures are another feature of functional programming languages that allow for techniques like composition.  However, due to the lack of block scope when using &lt;code&gt;var&lt;/code&gt;, this unfortunately ruins that advantage. Reading David Shariff&amp;rsquo;s article on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://davidshariff.com/blog/what-is-the-execution-context-in-javascript/&#34;&gt;Javascript Execution Context&lt;/a&gt; may clear up some things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t &lt;code&gt;let&lt;/code&gt; yourself be fooled.  &lt;code&gt;let&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt; are intended to replace &lt;code&gt;var&lt;/code&gt;, and while we&amp;rsquo;ll see old code on the web for quite some time, we are responsible for what developers will see in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, as per the code above - all you have to do is use &lt;code&gt;let&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;var funcs = [];

for (let i = 0; i &amp;lt; 3; i++) {
  funcs[i] = function() {
    console.log(&amp;quot;value of i: &amp;quot; + i);
  }
}

funcs.forEach(func =&amp;gt; func.call());

// &amp;quot;value of i: 0&amp;quot;
// &amp;quot;value of i: 1&amp;quot;
// &amp;quot;value of i: 2&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>To vim or not to vim</title>
      <link>https://ndonolli.github.io/post/vim/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2017 23:04:33 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ndonolli.github.io/post/vim/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ucarecdn.com/18f71672-5e94-4f74-9cf4-b840507509b0/&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not good with vim.  I use it for git commits and for when my &lt;em&gt;bash-fu&lt;/em&gt; is not strong enough to make file changes with one command.  I like it better than nano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a while now, I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to change my ways.  vim is everywhere.  It&amp;rsquo;s on Linux.  Linux is everywhere.  To achieve at least some level of proficiency with the vim text editor could give one a tremendous advantage working within a shell.  I grew tired of my walking-on-eggshells workflow of &lt;em&gt;press i -&amp;gt; press keys -&amp;gt; press ESC + :wq and pray&lt;/em&gt; to touch files, and decided enough was enough - &lt;strong&gt;I was going to actually learn vim.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it hasn&amp;rsquo;t happened yet.  I still switch to the arrow keys when my stream of &lt;em&gt;hjkls&lt;/em&gt; spaz out the cursor.  The other day I accidentally recorded a macro and didn&amp;rsquo;t know how to stop it (my current solution: quit vim). Yes, I could be devoting more time to it.  No, I haven&amp;rsquo;t set my IDE to vim mode.  Somewhere along the journey, possibly before it even started, I stopped caring.  And so the conflict remains: should I care?  Will learning vim make me a more effective software engineer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe the answer is a soft &lt;em&gt;maybe&lt;/em&gt;.  vim is old, but it withstood the test of time and won the hearts and minds of many a developer.  The fact that vim is more alive than ever is actually pretty amazing.  vim is older than I am - the first computer I recall using was an IBM Aptiva running Windows 95, which was released four years after vim and even longer after its precursor vi was a POSIX standard.  Modern computers can run newer, heavier IDEs with little difference in speed, and yet vim remains the IDE of choice for many veteran and even junior software developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I understand it, vim&amp;rsquo;s appeal is on two fronts: accessibility and speed. The speed aspect is due its specific set of bindings which, when learned, can allow you to quickly traverse and edit text without the need for a mouse or touchpad.  On top of that, vim&amp;rsquo;s bindings are organized by different modes, allowing modularity and a larger set of binding options.  Unfortunately, this is one of the primary hurdles of learning vim.  There are many key bindings, and they are not intuitive to users of modern text editors which utilize a different set of shortcuts.  Those who master the bindings, however, can blaze through a document with the ability to select specific patterns, move whole lines, and other specific features all without touching the mouse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.terminally-incoherent.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/vimcheat-640x272.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lesson 1: Hit your head against the keyboard repeatedly&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The accessibility aspect is due to the fact that vim exists on most UNIX and Linux flavored operating systems, and it runs in the terminal.  If you need to SSH into a remote server and edit a text file, you can bet you can do it with vim.  Existing as a command line application, vim has easy access to the rest of the system through its extensibility.  It is written in C but ships with its own scripting language used for plugins and extensions. If your vim looks underfeatured compared to your beefed up atom IDE, it&amp;rsquo;s probably because you never beefed up your vim.  Any modern vim user probably extends it with syntax highlighting, version control integration, directory trees - really anything you find in any new IDE.  And when you encounter vanilla vim on another machine?  Hey, you already know the bindings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should retract my previous statement. &lt;em&gt;I do care about learning vim&lt;/em&gt;.  It&amp;rsquo;s just work, and I can&amp;rsquo;t get over the irony that I&amp;rsquo;m doing work in order to become faster at, well, doing work.  What really intrigues me to learn is the accessibility advantage.  Like bash, vim is a program that lives on because &lt;em&gt;other people use it&lt;/em&gt;, and what other indication of quality software do you need?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the record, I hate writing bash scripts too.  Or rather, I used to hate it.  Once you get past the old-school, memory-saving syntax of this weird, geeky language - good god is it useful.  It&amp;rsquo;s the glue of Linux, and no higher-level python script can come close to taking its place.  The same applies to vim, probably for the next twenty years.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>at&amp;t_irl</title>
      <link>https://ndonolli.github.io/post/att/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2017 12:28:36 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ndonolli.github.io/post/att/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://d1sui4xqepm0ps.cloudfront.net/memes/1970-at-t-subsidiary-bell-labs-deve.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;memes can only express what words cannot&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Your React Native Drawer to Behave Juuuuuuust Right</title>
      <link>https://ndonolli.github.io/post/sexy-react-native-drawers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2017 12:52:20 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ndonolli.github.io/post/sexy-react-native-drawers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;native&amp;rdquo; half of React-native is why so many web developers get so giddy about it.  A technology that binds to native mobile platform APIs on top of the already-popular React library is a welcome addition to the new wave of web-to-mobile solutions, many of which rely on custom components rendered within webkit (which is also still great).  Where React-native shines is that your picker will look like an iOs picker, your buttons will fade that right way when you click it, and the app will just &amp;ldquo;feel&amp;rdquo; like a real app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this a reason to make the switch?  Not really.  The importance of having a &amp;ldquo;native feeling&amp;rdquo; app weighs on the product owner, and even within react-native, certain components aren&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; there yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But usually you can make due.  I&amp;rsquo;m a big fan of &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/root-two/react-native-drawer&#34;&gt;react-native-drawer&lt;/a&gt;, which gives you a customizable drawer component akin to the kind you see in many Android apps.  If you start with a boilerplate/generator that includes this package, the drawer will usually render with default settings that (in my opinion) do not mimic the look and feel of a typical Android drawer. The documentation can be a little spacey, so I&amp;rsquo;ll show you the few, small tweaks I make to get this looking right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bear with me for a sec - this is how the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;Drawer&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; component is rendered using a standard &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/infinitered/ignite&#34;&gt;Ignite&lt;/a&gt; template, a cli-interface generator I like to bootstrap react-native projects with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;Drawer
  ref=&#39;navigation&#39;
  type=&#39;displace&#39;
  open={state.open}
  onOpen={() =&amp;gt; NavigationActions.refresh({key: state.key, open: true})}
  onClose={() =&amp;gt; NavigationActions.refresh({key: state.key, open: false})}
  content={&amp;lt;DrawerContent /&amp;gt;}
  styles={Styles}
  tapToClose
  openDrawerOffset={0.2}
  panCloseMask={0.2}
  negotiatePan
  tweenHandler={(ratio) =&amp;gt; ({
    main: { opacity: Math.max(0.54, 1 - ratio) }
  })}
&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;DefaultRenderer navigationState={children[0]} onNavigate={this.props.onNavigate} /&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/Drawer&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem I&amp;rsquo;m addressing has to do with the &lt;strong&gt;animation&lt;/strong&gt; of the drawer open/close.  Mainly being:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The drawer displaces the screen when opened&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The screen fades to white, where most native apps fade to black.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The tween animation is rough and fast.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these issues can be solved by passing the right prop values into this component.  Take note:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;Drawer
  ref=&#39;navigation&#39;
  type=&#39;overlay&#39;
  open={state.open}
  onOpen={() =&amp;gt; NavigationActions.refresh({key: state.key, open: true})}
  onClose={() =&amp;gt; NavigationActions.refresh({key: state.key, open: false})}
  content={&amp;lt;DrawerContent /&amp;gt;}
  styles={Styles}
  tapToClose
  openDrawerOffset={0.2}
  panCloseMask={0.2}
  negotiatePan
  tweenHandler={(ratio) =&amp;gt; ({
    mainOverlay: {
      opacity: ratio / 2,
      backgroundColor: &#39;black&#39;
    },
    drawer: {
      shadowRadius: Math.min(ratio * 5 * 5, 5)
    }
  })}
  tweenEasing=&#39;easeOutQuint&#39;
  tweenDuration={800}
&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;DefaultRenderer navigationState={children[0]} onNavigate={this.props.onNavigate} /&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/Drawer&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, &lt;code&gt;type=&#39;displace&#39;&lt;/code&gt; can be changed to &lt;code&gt;type=&#39;overlay&#39;&lt;/code&gt; - solving that first issue easily.  The rest can be fixed by editing some of the tween configurations.  The &lt;code&gt;tweenHandler&lt;/code&gt;, for example, takes a function that manipulates other properties based on the current state of the animation sequence.  With this, we can get our faded black backround, as well as adding a dynamic &lt;code&gt;shadowRadius&lt;/code&gt; to give a popping effect that the drawer hovers above the screen.  As for the third point, the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; tween function can be determined by &lt;code&gt;tweenEasing&lt;/code&gt;, which takes a string corresponding to one of the functions defined in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/chenglou/tween-functions&#34;&gt;tween-functions&lt;/a&gt; package, which comes as a dependency with &lt;code&gt;react-native-drawer&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with the tween-function and other tweaks, you should experiment to find the drawer that fits your fancy. But never settle for less.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Meditation on Redux</title>
      <link>https://ndonolli.github.io/post/redux/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2016 18:34:37 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ndonolli.github.io/post/redux/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about Redux lately.  Everybody and their mother (and my mother) loves Redux, and that makes sense.  The Redux team &lt;em&gt;(read: Dan Abramov)&lt;/em&gt; bestows &lt;a href=&#34;http://redux.js.org/&#34;&gt;philosophical documentation&lt;/a&gt; that explain the three noble truths of Redux - the main one being that reducers are pure functions of state and action.  With immutable state, your application becomes much more predictable and testable.  If this sounds simple and you are asking why it isn&amp;rsquo;t just incorporated into the design of state-based rendering libraries like React, it&amp;rsquo;s because it kinda sorta is with flux, a library/design pattern used internally at Facebook of which Redux builds upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, really, there&amp;rsquo;s not much to Redux.  But developers view it like a god damn necessity. The first page of the docs provides a plea from the creator himself on why you might not need Redux. By not using Redux, you risk introducing scalability issues as your app grows.  By including Redux, you risk wasting time writing boilerplate for your state, actions, and reducers for a view change that could have just been triggered with &lt;code&gt;setState()&lt;/code&gt;.  The only way to know if you&amp;rsquo;ll need Redux is to use it.  And even after using it, I&amp;rsquo;m still not sure what to think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I digress, this is not really about Redux. Redux is fantastic. This is about me understanding how to use Redux properly.  Let me give you an example: in building &lt;strong&gt;Grubbr&lt;/strong&gt;, a mobile app designed with react-native, we spent a good amount of time including/excluding Redux in our tech stack, flip flopping through the reasons stated above.  Ultimately, our final project architecture was laid out with the help of a react-native boilerplate library called &lt;a href=&#34;http://nativebase.io/&#34;&gt;Nativebase&lt;/a&gt;.  We still structured our codebase from scratch since we intended to use Nativebase primarily as a UI library, but we also kept their custom routing plugin, which was controlled through Redux actions and reducers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here was the first potential design flaw of the application: All views were rendered inside this custom navigator component.  Any components that needed to be globally accessible had to have been included in the same tier as the navigator component.  This isn&amp;rsquo;t too bad, and our app was essentially a collection of separate, non-nested views anyway.  But now the traditional method of passing data to child elements through props and state has to be thrown out the window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where Redux kicked ass actually. Say we want a user object that contains their name, id, etc. and is created on login.  The id is used for any kind of POST request so the user object must be globally available to all views. Sure, we could use some cookie that contains some encrypted info, but why not set it simply to state?  With Redux, the global state persists throughout the whole application as a single object that contains state, route, location, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;function bindAction(dispatch) {
  return {
    openDrawer: () =&amp;gt; dispatch(openDrawer()),
    replaceRoute: route =&amp;gt; dispatch(replaceRoute(route)),
    pushNewRoute: route =&amp;gt; dispatch(pushNewRoute(route)),
    setIndex: index =&amp;gt; dispatch(setIndex(index)),
    popRoute: () =&amp;gt; dispatch(popRoute()),
    setCurrentDish: dish =&amp;gt; dispatch(setCurrentDish(dish)),
    setLocation: location =&amp;gt; dispatch(setLocation(location)),
  };
}
function mapStateToProps(state) {
  return {
    name: state.user.name,
    list: state.list.list,
    results: state.search,
    location: state.location.location,
  };
}
export default connect(mapStateToProps, bindAction)(BestInTown);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But like all alchemy, one must give up something in order to receive something in return. In our case, we have given up the ease of managing a local state to dictate changes in an individual component&amp;rsquo;s UI.  Here&amp;rsquo;s another example: I wanted to include animations that would occur while the search was being conducted on the page. My normal method would be to set a &lt;code&gt;loading: false&lt;/code&gt; property in the initial local state, and triggering &lt;code&gt;setState({ loading: true })&lt;/code&gt; while waiting for the server request to return.  But now I gotta touch three files and create separate actions and reducers for this feature to come to fruition!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what did I do? I just did it the way I knew how. The &amp;lsquo;Redux state&amp;rsquo; is a separate entity and is accessed through the props (thanks to a function which, believe it or not, is called &lt;code&gt;mapStateToProps&lt;/code&gt;) so theoretically you can handle both state objects without any fear that they would interfere with each other. The problem is that I felt dirty, like I had broken one of the pillars of the Redux way of truth. Concerns were still separated, with persisting data being held in the &amp;lsquo;Redux state&amp;rsquo; and primarily UI logic being handled thru the local state. But it&amp;rsquo;s all state to consider for the React DOM, and part of me feels like there could have been a better way to reason about things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the application worked marvelously, despite my concerns that views seemed to render two or three times too many. And I&amp;rsquo;ll say this - I believe it worked out because, in the end, Redux is a very natural, minimalistic suggestion to handling application state. It is a library, but not by much.  It&amp;rsquo;s more a way of thinking.  Take this example from the article explaining &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@dan_abramov/you-might-not-need-redux-be46360cf367#.9c7c0ared&#34;&gt;why you may not need Redux&lt;/a&gt; written by Dan Abramov himself.  He first shows us a typical counter example in react using state:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;
import React, { Component } from &#39;react&#39;;

class Counter extends Component {
  state = { value: 0 };

  increment = () =&amp;gt; {
    this.setState(prevState =&amp;gt; ({
      value: prevState.value + 1
    }));
  };

  decrement = () =&amp;gt; {
    this.setState(prevState =&amp;gt; ({
      value: prevState.value - 1
    }));
  };

  render() {
    return (
      &amp;lt;div&amp;gt;
        {this.state.value}
        &amp;lt;button onClick={this.increment}&amp;gt;+&amp;lt;/button&amp;gt;
        &amp;lt;button onClick={this.decrement}&amp;gt;-&amp;lt;/button&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
    )
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then refactors it using actions, reducers, and dispatchers. But there&amp;rsquo;s no Redux installed at all! It&amp;rsquo;s just the design pattern:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;import React, { Component } from &#39;react&#39;;

const counter = (state = { value: 0 }, action) =&amp;gt; {
  switch (action.type) {
    case &#39;INCREMENT&#39;:
      return { value: state.value + 1 };
    case &#39;DECREMENT&#39;:
      return { value: state.value - 1 };
    default:
      return state;
  }
}

class Counter extends Component {
  state = counter(undefined, {});

  dispatch(action) {
    this.setState(prevState =&amp;gt; counter(prevState, action));
  }

  increment = () =&amp;gt; {
    this.dispatch({ type: &#39;INCREMENT&#39; });
  };

  decrement = () =&amp;gt; {
    this.dispatch({ type: &#39;DECREMENT&#39; });
  };

  render() {
    return (
      &amp;lt;div&amp;gt;
        {this.state.value}
        &amp;lt;button onClick={this.increment}&amp;gt;+&amp;lt;/button&amp;gt;
        &amp;lt;button onClick={this.decrement}&amp;gt;-&amp;lt;/button&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
    )
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what should you use? Should you use Redux at all? Should you use it all the time? I implore you to meditate on this decision as I have done, and perhaps the wisdom of Dan Abramov will descend upon you. And he shall say &amp;lsquo;Yeah, probably&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working with geolocation on a non-secure site</title>
      <link>https://ndonolli.github.io/post/geolocation-non-secure/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2016 14:31:20 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ndonolli.github.io/post/geolocation-non-secure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The last couple of days, our small development team &lt;strong&gt;BrutSoft&lt;/strong&gt; was working on some legacy code written by our friend Harvey for his app &amp;ldquo;Pick-up&amp;rdquo;. It is a simple web-app that organizes pick-up soccer games, sending out texts through Twilio&amp;rsquo;s SMS service. We wanted to expand this app to work on a mobile platform through the Ionic framework, add an authentication service, and extra geolocation features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I opted to implement the geolocation features, initially utilizing the HTML5 native &lt;code&gt;navigator.geolocation&lt;/code&gt; API to grab the user&amp;rsquo;s location data and search for active games within a 10km radius. It was only after I had deployed the app that I learned that &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/updates/2016/04/geolocation-on-secure-contexts-only&#34;&gt;Google has discontinued support for geolocation on non-secure domains&lt;/a&gt;. Not wanting to deal with obtaining a SSL certificate, I quickly scrambled to find a new solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; I am in no way against Google&amp;rsquo;s decision to promote a safer web by requiring SSL certification for sensitive user information like geolocation. The beauty of the web is that many solutions exist and, so long as the web remains open, many problems will be solved and shared. This post is about one solution I found that worked for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not interested in changing the codebase dramatically, I started searching for a third-party API that offered geolocation services. I settled on &lt;a href=&#34;http://ipinfo.io&#34;&gt;ipinfo.io&lt;/a&gt; which is a light, RESTful service and offers 1000 free API calls per day. There are many more that would probably work fine and I encourage further research, but I was sold on the simplicity of using this service. My original code wrapped the &lt;code&gt;getCurrentPosition()&lt;/code&gt; method in a promise, and then sent the game request on resolve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;getLocation: function() {
  var options = {
    enableHighAccuracy: true,
    timeout: 5000,
    maximumAge: 0
  };

  return new Promise(function(resolve, reject) {
    navigator.geolocation.getCurrentPosition(resolve, reject, options);
  });
},
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;getCurrentPosition&lt;/code&gt; method is an asynchronous call, which necessitates the Promise wrapper in order to wait for the location to return before attaching it to the game request object, which is handled by an Angular controller.  Among the deprecation of this method for non-secure sites, there are a couple other things that are annoying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The browser will ask the user to grant the application permission to know their GPS location.  From a UX standpoint, this is not really ideal.  The native chrome alert box that pops up could seem a tad sketchy and insecure to some users, even if they were aware that the app used location to function.  It would be much better to ask for permission or inform the user through the app itself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If a user denies permission to reveal their location, whether on purpose or by accident, there is no way to reset this through the application.  The permissions are stored within the browser and there is no simple way to check, through your application, if a user has denied or granted geolocation permissions.  To the application, the &lt;code&gt;getLocation&lt;/code&gt; function will just timeout.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By using &lt;em&gt;ipinfo.io&lt;/em&gt; there is no need to ask permission, which in my opinion is redundant considering the app is very clear about how it uses user&amp;rsquo;s locations.  It is one less thing to worry about on the user experience end and several lines of code shorter for the developer who should not have to worry about handling that extra logic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;getLocation&lt;/code&gt; helper function was thus refactored to&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;getLocation: function() {
  return new Promise(function(resolve, reject) {
    $.getJSON(&#39;https://ipinfo.io/geo&#39;, resolve);
  });
},
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;which honestly isn&amp;rsquo;t that much different.  The return JSON data is mostly similar to how the Chrome geolocation object is structured, so just minor tweaks to the controller allowed this new code to fit in just dandily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;// ...
.controller(&#39;TimeSelectController&#39;, function($scope, $location, GameReq, sharedProps) {
  var gameReq = {};
  $scope.findingLocation = false;

  $scope.requestGame = function() {
    console.log(&#39;requesting Game&#39;);
    $scope.findingLocation = true;
    helpers.getLocation()
    .then(function(response) {
      var loc = response.loc.split(&#39;,&#39;);
      gameReq.location = {
        latitude: +loc[0],
        longitude: +loc[1],
      };
      gameReq.time = helpers.createGameTime($scope.data.selectedOption.hour);
      gameReq.smsNum = $scope.smsNum;
      gameReq.sport = $scope.sportInput;

      GameReq.requestGame(gameReq)
        // etc...      
    })
  }
})
// ...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, &lt;em&gt;ipinfo.io&lt;/em&gt; is one just one of many sites that offer geolocation as a service.  Find what works best for you if there comes a time where you can&amp;rsquo;t/don&amp;rsquo;t want to use the native geolocation features built into Chrome.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Objects of My Affliction</title>
      <link>https://ndonolli.github.io/post/objects-of-my-affliction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2016 12:02:51 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ndonolli.github.io/post/objects-of-my-affliction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Javascript objects are a cozy bunch.  To define an object in javascript in the most basic, literal sense, you would write:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;var myObject = {};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keys and values may then be defined with bracket or dot-notation syntax, and objects are all instantiations of the parent &lt;code&gt;Object&lt;/code&gt; of which it inherits other methods and properties.  This syntax for displaying objects in Javascript has helped me to understand how objects are
organized in other programming languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To a beginner, there are very easy-to-grasp similarities between the two languages.  Both have number and string datatypes, as well as similar syntax.  In both languages, arrays are designated with square brackets &lt;code&gt;[]&lt;/code&gt; and in general share similar properties.  However, Python utilizes curly (mustache?) brackets to denote a collection called a dictionary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again - on the surface, and especially to a beginner, there seems to be virtually no difference between Javascript&amp;rsquo;s objects and Python&amp;rsquo;s dictionaries.  Both are collections of key: value pairs - separated by commas with a colon between the key and value.  Take a look at this object in Javascript:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;var myObject = {&#39;foo&#39;: &#39;bar&#39;};
myObject[&#39;foo&#39;] // =&amp;gt;&#39;bar&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;and then this dictionary in Python:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;my_dictionary = {&#39;foo&#39;: &#39;bar&#39;};
my_dictionary[&#39;foo&#39;] // =&amp;gt; &#39;bar&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The differences here are cosmetic - Javascript requires the var keyword to declare a variable (kind of) whereas this is not required in Python.  Also, convention states that Javascript uses camel case where Python uses underscores.  But the initialization and retrieval of key: value pairs is almost identical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But are Python dictionaries objects?  Technically, everything is an object in Python, but dictionaries !== objects in Javascript.  Here&amp;rsquo;s another example of a small difference.  In Python, we can set a variable as a key in a dictionary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;i = &#39;k&#39;
j = 1
dict = {i: j}
dict[&#39;k&#39;] // =&amp;gt; 1
dict[i] // =&amp;gt; 1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;but trying the same thing in Javascript&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;var i = &#39;k&#39;
var j = 1
var obj = {i: j}
obj[&#39;k&#39;] // =&amp;gt; undefined
obj[i] // =&amp;gt; undefined
obj[&#39;i&#39;] // =&amp;gt; 1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that accessing &lt;code&gt;dict[&#39;i&#39;]&lt;/code&gt; would return undefined in Python, since it would be looking for the string &lt;code&gt;&#39;i&#39;&lt;/code&gt; as a key.  In Javascript, object keys are stored as strings and must be passed in as such when accessing with bracket notation.  Here is another example that exemplifies this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In javascript, we can declare a literal object like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;var obj = {name: &#39;Nathan&#39;}
console.log(obj) // =&amp;gt; [object Object] {name: &#39;Nathan&#39;}
console.log(obj[&#39;name&#39;]) // =&amp;gt; &#39;Nathan&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in python we would get an error:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; obj = {name: &#39;Nathan&#39;}
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File &amp;quot;&amp;lt;input&amp;gt;&amp;quot;, line 1, in &amp;lt;module&amp;gt;
NameError: name  &#39;name&#39; is not defined
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get the error because the variable name is undefined, so Python raises the &lt;code&gt;NameError&lt;/code&gt; when given the key to obj.  In Javascript&amp;rsquo;s literal object notation, the keys within the brackets are converted to string datatypes.  We are now getting to the core of the difference between Javascript objects and Python dictionaries - which is, well, that Javascript objects are objects with properties and methods, which can inherit from parent objects and be used as a prototype for child objects.  Python dictionaries are more akin to mapped lists, in which each key can store a pointer or piece of data.  Both languages use bracket notation as constructors for these respective datatypes - and though they look similar, they vary greatly in their behaviors.  Here is one parting example, showing how Javascript objects can contain methods while Python dictionaries can store functions but not invoke them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Javascript:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;var obj = {
  name: &#39;Nathan&#39;,
  myName: function() {return obj.name;}
};

console.log(obj.myName()) // =&amp;gt; &#39;Nathan&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can call the method &lt;code&gt;myName&lt;/code&gt; with dot notation, which returns the property &lt;code&gt;name&lt;/code&gt; in obj. However in python:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;def func():
  return dict[&#39;name&#39;]

dict = {
  &#39;name&#39;: &#39;Nathan&#39;,
  &#39;myName&#39;: func
}

dict[&#39;myName&#39;] // =&amp;gt; &amp;lt;function func at 0x100756f28&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accessing &lt;code&gt;myName&lt;/code&gt; in dict gives us a pointer to the function we declared earlier in the code.  It is not an object method, and thus cannot be invoked the same way we could in Javascript.  The object literal notation is a very convenient way to create and manipulate objects within Javascript, but it&amp;rsquo;s important to recognize that it is also an abstract datatype, and the brackets are just a symbol to denote its data.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://ndonolli.github.io/projects/minesweeper/README/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ndonolli.github.io/projects/minesweeper/README/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;super-simple-minesweeper&#34;&gt;Super Simple Minesweeper&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend once told me a story of how, during an interview, they were asked to implement the hit Windows 95&amp;trade; game &amp;ldquo;Minesweeper&amp;rdquo; within a time limit.  This is my awful attempt, for science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-why&#34;&gt;But&amp;hellip;why?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that you may learn.  And I may learn.  And you may learn from what I have learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-how&#34;&gt;But&amp;hellip;how?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just clone this repo&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/ndonolli/minesweeper-example.git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;and open up index.html in your browser.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://ndonolli.github.io/projects/minesweeper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ndonolli.github.io/projects/minesweeper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
  &lt;meta charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;
  &lt;meta name=&#34;viewport&#34; content=&#34;width=device-width&#34;&gt;
  &lt;script src=&#34;https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/jquery/3.2.1/jquery.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;script src=&#34;index.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;style&gt;
  h1 {
    text-align: center;
  }
  table {
    margin: 10px auto;
  }
  td {
    border: 1px solid;
    width: 50px;
    height: 50px;
    text-align: center;
  }
  .bomb {
      background-color: indianred;
  }
  #table-container {
    align-content: center;
  }
  &lt;/style&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;Minesweeper&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
  &lt;h1&gt;MINESWEEPER!!&lt;/h1&gt;
  &lt;div id=&#34;table-container&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>